Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, we page today's דף יד, Daf Yud
Dalet, we pick up in the middle of יג עמוד ב, Yud
Gimmel Amud Bet, we first are finishing up the משנה Mishnah about
that and the גמרא Gemara related discussion in the גמרא Gemara about
זרע לבטלה. Zera L'vatala. We have one last comment on that and
then we'll move on. So it is middle of יג עמוד ב
Yud Gimmel Amud Bet about 20 lines down, the two dots, באנשים
תקצץ, Banashim Ketzatzot, so after an a longer discussion about various types
of things which are forbidden
for intentional and the exhortations around intentional acts of masturbation
or even unintentional, now we have the line in the משנה Mishnah
that speaks that says that the hand that is frequently does it
for men, but the גמרא Gemara paraphrased it not even frequently, forbidden
even infrequently, but nevertheless used the phrase should be cut off. So
now the גמרא Gemara asks how literal that is. איבעיא להו, Iba'u
Lehu, so we ask the question, this is about 10 lines before
the lines get wide. דינא תנן או ליטותא תנן? Dina Tenan o
Litusa Tenan?
Is it literally the law that you cut off the hand? Oh
my god that's so terrible. Or is it a curse? Let's take
a look. דינא תנן, Dina Tenan, it would be a law? כי
הא דרב הונא קץ ידה, Ki Ha DeRav Huna Katz Yadah, there's
a story that רב הונא Rav Huna actually cut off somebody's hand.
Again you wonder if this is really literal. The גמרא Gemara in
סנהדרין Sanhedrin says that it's forbidden to raise your hand against your
friend, and if you raise your hand against your friend it's deserving
of being cut off, and then it says that רב הונא Rav
Huna actually did it. Scary to think about. או ליטותא תנן, O
Litusa Tenan, or is it a curse? תא שמע, Ta Shema, come
hear, תניא רבי טרפון אומר, Tanya Rabbi Tarfon Omer, יד אל האמה
תקצץ, Yad El Ha'amah Tikatzeitz, if a hand goes to a man
brings his hand to his genitals, literally to his penis, it should
be cut off. יד אל טבורו תקצץ, Yad El Taburo Tikatzeitz, his
hand should be cut off on his belly button. אמרו לו, Amru
Lo, the rabbi said back to him, ולא כריסה נבקעת, Velo Kresa
Nipkat, but if you cut off his hand on his belly button
you'll cut open his stomach.
אמר להן Amar Lahen he said to them, מוטב תבקע כריסו, Mutav
Tibakei Kreso, remember the thing about מוטב Mutav the kids should be
seen as ממזרים, Mamzeirim, better the stomach should be rent open, ואל
ירד לבאר שחת, Ve'al Yered Li've'er Shachat, rather than he should go
into you know the netherworld, into the depths, into hell. So now
we're going to analyze. אי אמרת בשלמא דינא תנן, Iy Amart Bishlama
Dina Tenan, if we're being literal, היינו דאמרי ולא כריסה נבקעת, Hainu
De'amri Velo Kresa Nipkat, then you could have a question, if you're
literally cutting his hand on his belly button you're going to cut
open his stomach. אלא אי אמרת ליטותא תנן, Ella Iy Amart Litusa
Tenan, but if it was just a curse and figurative, מאי כריסה
נבקעת, Mai Kresa Nipkat, what are they worried about his belly button
his stomach being open? Figuratively anyway what are they worried about? אלא
מאי, Ella Mai, so what do you think? דינא תנן, Dina Tenan,
we're being
literal, לא סגי דלאו על טבורו? Lo Sagi Delav Al Taburo? It
doesn't make sense anyway cutting off his hand on his belly button,
like why should that have been important? Why would that have been
necessary? אלא, Ella, so we have to understand what's going on here.
It really doesn't mean cut off his hand on his belly button.
הכי קאמר רבי טרפון. Hachi Ka'amar Rabbi Tarfon. Here's
what רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is saying. כל המכניס ידו למטה
מן הטבור, Kol Hamachnis Yado Lematah Min HaTaburo, that the belly button
is not where you're cutting the hand off. It's where you can't
bring your hand down. Anybody who lowers his hand to the nether
regions, any man obviously to of his body below his navel, תקצץ,
Tikatzeitz, should be cut off and here we're going to obviously say
mean deserving of being cut off, it's again figurative. אמרו לו לרבי
טרפון, Amru Lo LeRabbi Tarfon, so now here we're going to see
about the concern of the stomach opening up, not that we're reading
this word literally, but they said רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, ישב לו
קוץ בכריסו לא יטלנו? Yashav Lo Kotz BeKreso Lo Yitlenu? Let's say
the person's got like a splinter below his navel, he actually has
to do something in the area of his body, a medical need,
what should he do? You're telling me he shouldn't actually move his
hand down there to remove it? אמר להן לא, Amar Lahen Lo,
he said no, that's why don't do anything. ולאו כריסה נבקעת? Velo
Kresa Nipkat? But won't that cause his stomach to burst open? Again
that might also be figurative, but you know that'll lead to problems.
אמר להן מוטב תבקע כריסו ואל ירד לבאר שחת, Amar Lahen Mutav
Tibakei Kreso Ve'al Yered Li've'er Shachat, I'd rather that you have whatever
medical problems you have and you don't go down into the netherworld.
Very strange, all of these are very strange, right? Like the גמרא
Gemara before that we had yesterday, better that you should people should
think your sons are ממזרים, Mamzeirim, your children are ממזרים, Mamzeirim, rather
than that you should you know even touch that area even incidentally.
So a lot of exhortations in the גמרא, Gemara, at least the
גמרא, Gemara, I mean the הוה אמינא Havah Aminah is more disturbing
than the conclusion. I don't think it would have even occurred to
us to read the line literally, so it's not such a consolation
that the גמרא Gemara in the end says, okay we read it
figuratively. Anyway at the end of the day, we've read a lot
of גמרא. Gemara.
So are they are they a decision that?
Yeah, it seems to be the גמרא's Gemara happy to come I
know with all you're right with all discussions in the גמרא Gemara
it raises a possibility and says no you don't have to say
that you could say that but
we're left with the
with the indecision one possibility
is their hand is actually
yes although the sense you get like whenever גמרא Gemara sort of
says something and rejects it the sense although it doesn't conclude one
way the sense you get is is that it's preferring sort of
the last thing.
approach, the תורה Torah of the woman who's grabbed and fighting and
it says her
hand and as the גמרא Gemara interprets that figuratively, correct. But nevertheless
kind of left a
little ambiguous, right.
I mean certainly the assumption is that it's figurative, but you are
right it's not conclusive and it leaves it a little ambiguous. Now
in general, just one final comment about this before we move on,
which is like there was a lot of very strong exhortations in
the גמרא, Gemara, you know, deserving of curse, deserving of the hand
cut off, that the children are seen to be ממזרים, Mamzerim, you
know, children of the מבול, Mabul, all of these, it's like you
killed, it's like you whatever. And the question becomes again, you know,
how does that translate in terms of הלכה Halacha weight? What's the
הלכה Halacha significance of all that? I mean the גמרא Gemara says
a number of things. גמרא Gemara says anybody who gets angry, it's
like they're עובד עבודה זרה. Oved Avodah Zarah. Anybody who has גאוה,
Gaavah, it's like he's עובד עבודה זרה. Oved Avodah Zarah. You know,
anybody who's not עוסק בפריה ורביה Osek Be'piryah Ve'rivyah is כאילו שופך
דמים. Ke'ilu Shofech Damim.
So you know, there are other types of ways in which the
גמרא Gemara uses, you know, hyperbole to speak about how terrible it
is and sometimes tapping into what part of the concern is, right?
Not having a lot of children or whatever, not being עוסק בפריה
ורביה Osek Be'piryah Ve'rivyah is כאילו שופך דמים Ke'ilu Shofech Damim because
you're not bringing life into the world. So there's obviously it's not
just hyperbole, it's hyperbole that's tapping into a nature of the concern,
but again it doesn't mean literal, it's כאילו Ke'ilu as if. So
anyway, there's really questions about this and there's an interesting debate in
the פוסקים, Poskim, how prohibited is really, is זרע לבטלה? Zera Le'vatala?
Some assume because the גמרא Gemara quotes this story of ער ואונן
Er Ve'onan and because it uses all this heavy language that it's
דאורייתא, De'oraita, although never, you know, there's never any פסוק Pasuk here
that the גמרא Gemara says look, this says you shall not do
this, so there's definitely are a lot of פוסקים Poskim that assume
that it's only דרבנן. De'rabbanan. But then the question beyond just the
narrow question about the weight, the technical הלכה Halacha weight, comes sort
of the religious weight that we assign to it, like how heavy
of a sin it is,
and you know that played very majorly in the for the קבליסטים
Kabbalists and for חסידים, Chasidim, that this was like one of the,
or maybe the worst sin that a person could do. You know,
even for in the זוהר Zohar I believe it's worse to be
מוציא זרע לבטלה Motzi Zera Le'vatala for a man than to have
sex with a non-Jewish woman who was not his wife or something.
So you know, and the idea that when you מוציא זרע לבטלה
Motzi Zera Le'vatala you give birth to evil spirits because then it's
all this unformed life that has not sort of reached its, you
know, its
proper
potential or whatever, right, connected with the woman feeds so it leads
to שדים Shedim and so on, and you know if you read
some of the וידוים Viduim around יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the heavy
emphasis on זרע לבטלה. Zera Le'vatala. So this becomes like a major
thing which its weight in, you know, in sort of the religious
mindset and certainly, you know, the guilt factor is huge compared to
the question of technically how much of a prohibition it actually is.
And it raises very serious questions, you know, nowadays because obviously, you
know, especially as people and you know it's a I think a
larger challenge, I'm not saying it's not a challenge for women too,
but we discussed the issue the other day about how much הלכה,
Halacha, you know, is concerned or addresses that, but people getting married
at a later age, you know, in time of the גמרא Gemara
they were so concerned about having הרהורים Hirhurim and whatever that it
advised boys to get married fifteen, seventeen, or whatever. So it really
raises very serious, you know, issues and just yesterday we mentioned the
whole question about even when it's for clearly a legitimate purpose like
for because a couple can't have children without taking semen from the
man, you know, how much does this become like a huge
issue even when it's done for a licit purpose. So there's definitely
a lot of ways in which this presents real sort of challenges
for the religious psyche and for הלכה Halacha issues that come up,
you know, as a result of this גמרא Gemara and this is
really the central discussion for all this, so I'm obviously not going
to resolve it here but I just wanted to raise all of
those issues.
But when it comes to the קבליסטים Kabbalists and the חסידים, Chasidim,
you have to ask is any of this Christian?
That's an interesting question or did, you know, which way did the
influence go. I mean but it is true that Christians had, you
know, their whole issue with the priests and celibacy and somewhat, you
know, that that, you know, the greater sort of, that's true, the
greater negativity towards sex is much more, you know, is very heavy
in Christian thought. And that is a question, what's his name in
his book on Eros and the Jews, Biale, David Biale and others
discuss the question about, you know, how much in the גמרא Gemara
the attitude towards sex, not זרע לבטלה Zera Le'vatala but marital sex,
and not that there's no anxiety but it tends to be overwhelmingly
positive and
in the ראשונים Rishonim there's a lot more anxiety and negativity around
it and there are those questions about influence from, you know, from
Christians and so on.
I was going to say the Christian asceticism towards sex goes all
the way back to the beginning.
Right,
right, especially with the חסידים Chasidim because
probably not in the בבלי, Bavli, it probably doesn't have that much
influence. Right. Okay, so moving on. So definitely Anyway, but now we're
back to the women. So, the חירשת, Chereshet, the woman who is
a deaf-mute, is normally how חירשת Chereshet is explained, which is not
considered to be of sort of of capable mind, sound mind. The
שוטה, Shota, literally somebody who is, insane is the wrong word, that's
more technical term, but it's sort of somebody who is also just
not. Yeah, not of well-mind and not sort of fully cognizant of
their awareness of their surroundings. והסומא, VehaSuma,
a blind person, which is interesting. Because they can't see, right? Well,
right. I know. ושניטרפה דעתה, VeShenitrefa Daatah, or again now the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask how is that different than a שוטה,
Shota, a woman who is whose sort of you know mind reasoning
has been confused. אם יש להן פקחות, Im Yesh Lahen Pikchos, if
they have intelligent, intelligent here doesn't mean like do well on the
IQ, just means don't have, what, a win? No, no, no, no,
we're talking about women, it's other women who are פקחות. Pikchos. Oh,
פיקח Pike'ach is contrast to חרש Cheresh and שוטה, Shoteh, it means
somebody of sound mind. If they have friends of sound mind, מתקנות
אותן, Metaknot Otan, they can fix them, meaning they can have their
friends check them and for and make sure that they are not
נידות Niddot והן אוכלות בתרומה Vehen Ochlot BiTruma which would then allow
them to eat תרומה. Truma. So their status can be determined not
by they themselves, but through the help of their friends, they can
their status can be determined and therefore what they touch won't be
a problem and they can eat תרומה Truma if they're married or
the daughters of כהנים. Kohanim.
They're presumably not handling תרומה Truma all the time, so this is
just
a concern when they want to eat it, right?
Or they could be, if their friends are checking them. Like, but
then they have to do that twice a day and right, correct.
And that's basically they say they should rely on their friends.
And then were their friends checked them before they, you know,
if they're married, I guess these women are assumed to be married?
That's an interesting question. Yeah, that's a good question. What does it
mean their friends check them? Internally?
Their friends are doing the internal exam? Right, I mean in theory
you could say it means they do the internal exam and the
friends look at it, but it doesn't sound like that because it
seems like the concern is also whether doing the internal exam correctly.
I mean if you look at רש"י, Rashi, מתקנות אותן בודקות אותן,
Metaknot Otan Bodkot Otan, they do the actual check and then רש"י
Rashi also has מטבילין אותן Matbilin Otan to make sure that they're
going to the מקוה. Mikveh. So they basically need to be, you
know, you can't trust them to do anything correctly, but you can
rely on their friends. So let's take a look at what the
גמרא Gemara says about this. Yeah, talk about like the objectifying here,
but it's better than sort of completely casting them out of society
I think and basically saying, you know, you're taboo and you have
to you know, definitely they don't have to eat תרומה. Truma.
That's true, they could make that choice, don't eat תרומה. Truma. But
still, everything they would touch would always be assumed to be טמא.
Tamei. But okay, they could make that choice.
But what if the
woman's the daughter of a כהן? Kohen? Exactly. Okay, so כהן Kohen
doesn't have only תרומה. Truma. I mean they could make that choice.
Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. חירשת, Chereshet, says the גמרא, Gemara, חירשת
Chereshet a woman who's deaf or deaf-mute, חירשת Chereshet can sometimes mean
deaf, sometimes deaf-mute, תבדוק לעצמה, Tibdok LeAtzma, let her check herself. דתניא
אמר רבי, DeTanya Amar Rabbi, Rabbi says, and there by the way
the גמרא Gemara is explaining תבדוק Tibdok that what they're doing is
not presumably תבדוק Tibdok doesn't just mean look at the cloth, but
תבדוק את עצמה, Tibdok Et Atzmah, check herself means the actual internal
check. דתניא אמר רבי, DeTanya Amar Rabbi, Rabbi says, חירשת היתה בשכונתנו,
Chereshet Hayta BiShekhunatenu,
we had a deaf or deaf-mute, we'll see in a minute, in
our neighborhood, לא דיה שבודקת לעצמה Lo Dayah SheBodeket LeAtzma
not only did she check herself, אלא שחברותיה רואות ומראות לה Ella
SheChaveroteha Ro'ot VeMar'ot Lah
that actually she was the neighborhood יועצת הלכה Yoetzet Halakha that her
friends when they had spots and stains, they would show her and
they would ask her what the הלכה Halakha is. So here you
go, not here's the first time we don't only have a woman's
voice like the maid of רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, but we actually
have a woman who's paskening for her friends. And she was a
חירשת. Chereshet. So you see a חירשת Chereshet could totally be of
sound mind. Who cares that she can't hear?
But no קול אשה. Kol Isha.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says התם במדברת ואינה שומעת, Hatam BiMedabberet
VeEina Shoma'at,
that's just that she's deaf. If she's deaf, that doesn't change her
halakhic status at all. And what we do find out in passing
here is women paskening for themselves about these issues. הכא Hakha why
do we say that she's not considered to be of sound mind?
בשאינה מדברת ואינה שומעת BiSheEina Medabberet VeEina Shoma'at she can neither speak
nor hear. דתנן DeTnan like we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, חרש
שדיברו חכמים בכל מקום Cheresh SheDibberu Chakhamim BeKhol Makom whenever the חכמים
Chakhamim speak about חרש, Cheresh, which is in the category of people
of not sound mind, אינו שומע ואינו מדבר Eino Shome'a VeEino Medabber
is somebody that neither can hear nor speak. Now, this is a
very big topic which I'm not going to unpack right now, but
obviously the, you know, the point was at the time when they
did not were not able to educate people that were deaf-mute. And
but if the person can speak, it seems to be why does
speaking make you more of sound mind? Well, it doesn't make you
of sound mind, but if you can speak intelligently then it shows
that even though you can't hear everything is still, but if you
can't speak and you're just gesturing and you can't hear what's coming
in, you can't understand, then it, you know, it basically made assumptions
that you don't know what's going on. And the question and you
know they obviously did not have other ways of communicating and most
people
were literate and so on, right? I mean if you could write
So the גמרא Gemara actually talks about a חרש המדבר מתוך הכתב.
cheresh hamedaber mitoch haksav. The גמרא Gemara actually talks about a חרש
cheresh that can communicate by writing changes the status. Anyway nowadays there's
major discussions about deaf mutes that can obviously communicate through sign language
and other types of things and clearly are intelligent. Whether they have
the same status or not and clearly there's an inclination of פוסקים
poskim to say they don't have the status of a לאו בר
דעת. lav bar da'as. Okay but that is a larger discussion than
we're having right now. Yeah I mean any issue about that about
is going to be debated. Anyway הסומא hasuma now blind person. So
the גמרא Gemara presumably the רמב"ם Rambam at least understood because you
can't look at the מראה. mara. But the גמרא Gemara says who
cares אי תבדוק נפשה ee tivdok nafsha let her check do the
actual physical check ותחזי לחברתה vetachzei l'chavertah
and let her show
the cloth to the friends let the friends look at the cloth
but let her do the physical check. So אמר רב יוסף ברבי
חנינא Amar Rav Yosef b'Rebbi Chanina סומא אינה במשנה. suma eina bamishna.
You're right סומא suma doesn't belong in the משנה mishna cross it
out. And if it's so which is always fascinating I mean what
is it there now they say? So again maybe in the maybe
at one time it meant that she part of it has to
rely on the friends for checking of it not the whole part
but part of it. Okay ושניטרפה דעתה v'shinitraufa da'atah or her or
her mind got confused or so היינו שוטה hainehu shota that's exactly
the case about the person not of sound mind.
So the גמרא Gemara says שניטרפה דעתה מחמת חולי. shnitrafa da'atah machmat
choli. No a שוטה shota is somebody that's like it's a permanent
state somebody that really is never of sound mind. ניטרפה דעתה nitrafa
daita is the whole the whole term temporary. Well right meaning somebody
that's right now is in the middle of some type of psychotic
fit right so you can understand so it's a temporary that's the
phrase it happens that her intellect has been confused it's not her
ongoing state.
Okay so I assume that they're out of it.
What? Yeah so there's גמרות Gemaras that discuss how do you assess
whether somebody is a שוטה shota and is not a שוטה shota
and whatever. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this תנו רבנן.
tnu rabbanan.
Now it's interesting by the way I should say that who's not
on this list?
Who's not on the list?
The young girls.
Who's the third of yeah קטנה k'tano חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shota
v'katan. חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shota v'katan. The
גמרא Gemara certainly has קטנות k'tanot what we had a whole משנה
mishna about קטנות k'tanot and whether they're considered מסובכת דמים mesuvakes damim
so maybe that's why they're not on the list maybe they're מסובכת
דמים mesuvakes damim in a general but we did say according to
תוספות Tosafot that even people who are מסובכת דמים mesuvakes damim have
to check twice and תוספות Tosafot says that includes
קטנות ktanot
because we learned as תוספות Tosafot says that שכינותיה shechnoteha check her
out. Didn't we have that?
Not by קטנות ktanot did we? Oh no it did say you're
right it said about her סחוטותיה. sachototeha.
Was that because yeah that was on yeah you're right י"ב ע"ב
yud amud bet it says חזקת בנות ישראל עד שלא יבואו לידי
היא הרי היא בחזקת טהרה ואין הנשים בודקות עצמן משיגיעו הרי היא
בחזקת טומאה ונשים בודקות אותן.
Cheskasa benos Yisrael ad shelo
yavo l'yadei harei
hi b'cheskas tahara v'ein honashim bodkos atzman misheyagiyu hare hi b'cheskas tuma
v'nashim bodkos osan.
Yeah Michael is correct right. Once they got to the age of
puberty although of course then they're adults but they could maybe have
physical signs of puberty and not being adults yet. Right the גמרא
Gemara in י"ג ע"ג yud amud gimmel does mention that that the
friends check the קטנות ktanot as well. It's interesting exact well it's
a ברייתא braita it's interesting that it's not in this משנה. mishna.
It generally raises the question of when you speak about a בר
דעת bar da'as how much is it a formal category and how
much is it just a practical question of can you trust the
person do they know what they're doing? Right like you can have
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shota v'katan it's all very nice but a
minute ago we spoke about what if the חרש cheresh they're intelligent
what if a קטן katan you can have lots of people that
are under בר ובת מצווה bar and bat mitzva that are highly
intelligent and it's quite evident. So there's a formal question about okay
but does the law recognize them able to execute
transactions or able to enter into contracts or whatever? That's like a
formalist legal category. But here it might be a practical question of
just can they be trusted to have done the job well? So
it is interesting that it's not in the משנה mishna but Michael
correctly remembers that it was an earlier גמרא. Gemara.
Precisely precisely it is quite test you can do it three times.
I understand that's what I'm saying it's an interesting question. תנו רבנן
Tnu rabbanan we talked. כהן שוטה מטבילין אותו Kohen shota matbilin oso
so now we balance it a little bit by talking about men.
Let's say you have a כהן kohen who's a שוטה shota who
cannot be trusted so how can he eat his own
תרומה? truma? And presumably there's a concern that he will either he
came in contact with something טמא tamei or
he he's a
בעל קרי ba'al keri he has a seminal emission and obviously that's
you can assume that'll happen from time to time maybe even married.
So how do you make sure that he's טהור tahor to go
to the מקווה? mikva? So also people have to oversee it. מטבילין
אותו Matbilin oso they dunk him ומאכילין אותו תרומה לערב umachilin oso
truma la'erev and they feed him תרומה truma at the night ומשמרים
אותו שלא יישן umeshamim oso shelo yishan but they have to make
sure that he eats תרומה truma right you have to wait till
sunset to be totally טהור tahor but he can only truma that
night. Once he falls asleep he can't eat תרומה truma because once
he falls asleep he might have a קרי keri he might have
had a seminal emission. They do that in the day too. What?
I know but well if you didn't see something happen you wouldn't
be concerned about that. Okay.
Maybe they go to like touch
שרץ sheretz oh I see but I guess again those are things
you're not normally concerned about. I guess it's true, if you walked
in like a מבוי mavo'i that was not cleaned out or whatever,
that might raise some concerns.
Okay. ומשמשין אותו שלא יישן, ישן, umishamshin oto shelo yishan, yashan, once
he sleeps, טמא, tamei, he's טמא. tamei. לא ישן טהור, lo yashan
tahor, if not he's טהור. tahor. So on the one hand, you
don't have the intrusive thing about physically checking him, right? On the
other hand, so it's less intrusive than we have by the women.
On the other hand, it's less intrusive because we're going to assume
he's טמא tamei whenever the possibility arises. As soon as he sleeps,
we assume he's טמא. tamei. Okay, of course the consequence is it's
a lot easier to make him טהור. tahor. Just go to the
מקווה mikvah and you're טהור tahor that night, as opposed to a
woman who requires seven days. Okay.
What? And he's only able to eat תרומה terumah at night. If
he wants to eat תרומה, terumah, this כהן שוטה, kohen shoteh, he
has to people have to oversee him going to the מקווה mikvah
day, and he can only eat תרומה terumah until he falls asleep.
Okay. רבי אליעזר ברבי צדוק אומר, Rabbi Eliezer Berabbi Tzadok omer, Rabbi
Eliezer bar Tzadok says, עושין לו כיס של עור. osin lo kis
shel or.
Actually, we don't assume as soon as he sleeps he's טהור, tahor,
he's טמא. tamei. You actually make for him a type of a
leather
literally cup, like to put on, you know, a type of underwear,
so that then you can check it and see if there's anything
on it the next morning. So it's tight-fitting. אמרו לו, amru lo,
they said to him, כל שכן שמביא לידי חימום, kol sheken shemevi
lidei himum, no, if it's tight-fitting, that'll cause him to be heated
up, meaning that'll cause sexual stimulation and excitement, that'll increase the problem.
And presumably you can't check it so well, maybe it gets absorbed
in the leather and so on, that's we're not going to rely
on that. That'll make things worse, worse. אמר להם, amar lahem, he
said back to them, לדבריכם, lidvreichem, שוטה אין לו תקנה, shoteh ein
lo takkanah, he said according to you the שוטה shoteh is going
to have a, you know, he won't be able to have any
solution. Now not no solution, sure, go to the מקווה mikvah and
eat at night, but it's going to make his life very hard,
you know, that, so that's not a satisfactory solution is what he
said to them. אמרו לו, amru lo, they said back to him,
לדברינו, lidvreinu, no, we have a solution. ישן טמא, לא ישן טהור.
yashan tamei, lo yashan tahor. Yes, we do have a solution. After
he sleeps it's a problem, but as long as he hasn't slept
from the time he's gone to the מקווה, mikvah, he's טהור. tahor.
That's, so we have a solution. לדבריך, lidvrecha, but according to you,
you, you say for us we make life hard. We might make
life hard, but at least we don't do איסורים. issurim. According to
you,
לדבריך, lidvrecha, שמא יראה טיפה כחרדל ותבלע בכיס, shema yireh tippah kehardal
vetibala bakkis, there'll be a tiny drop of semen as small as
a mustard seed. I don't know if anybody's ever seen a mustard
seed, it's extremely tiny, was used as a metaphor in the ancient
world for things that are infinitesimal. Abby, both Mike and Ari are
aware of some references for that. Anyway, and it'll be absorbed into
the, it'll be absorbed into the pouch. So therefore, we at least,
okay, we're strict, we make life hard, but we're not, but there's
no concern he's really טמא. tamei. According to you, he might actually
be טמא. tamei. תנא משום רבי אליעזר, tana mishum Rabbi Eliezer, they
tana in the name of Rabbi Eliezer, אמרו לו, amru lo, they
said,
עושין לו כיס של
מתכת.
osin lo kis
shel matechet.
So right, משום רבי אליעזר אמרו, mishum Rabbi Eliezer amru, in the
name of Rabbi Eliezer they said, so Rabbi Eliezer, this was Rabbi
Eliezer's solution. Oh, you're concerned about the leather? Fine, we'll make it
metal. And therefore you'll be able to see, well, I hope, probably
not too tight, I mean, you know, whatever, but it's a
serious, this is a serious
solution being suggested.
Why not just not eat תרומה? terumah?
Well, no, תרומה terumah is a lot cheaper than חולין. hullin. If
you're a כהן kohen and you get free תרומה, terumah, but if
you're a כהן kohen that's in some way
that could be a solution, impaired.
Right, then let the community,
no like you said, well, like you said by the משנה, Mishnah,
if they want to opt that way, they're free to opt that
way. You know, nobody's forcing him to eat תרומה, terumah, but if,
you know, but if there's, but if money is tight and you
have cheap תרומה, terumah, you want a solution to this problem. I
mean, nobody's forcing it, it's an option of how what you do
if you want to eat תרומה. terumah. All
right, so anyway, but it is, yeah, I mean, look, I don't
think these solutions are so crazy. I mean, I guess the metal
thing could be, well, the question again, you know, could be that
if it's that there's leather, you know, whatever, there's cloth where it's
tightened to the body, but the central section is metal.
Anyway, and this of course is right, I mean, that's really the
focus of the גמרא, Gemara, but this is someone who is like
a ward of the community. It's not like he's going to decide
am I going to eat תרומה terumah
today
or am I going to eat חולין? hullin? Well, maybe he's, maybe
he's being, maybe he's somebody's son, and he's in a house and
they don't have a lot of money and they want to feed
their son תרומה, terumah, right? I don't think he has to be
a, I don't know, I mean, you don't have to do these
things.
It's a very נעבעך nebbich thing to try to treat someone who's
impaired, is mentally impaired.
But I understand, but I think it's an option. I mean, you're
just saying if
you're imagining that the community, yes, and this
is just positing a what-if? Right, it's hypothetical. Right, I mean, that's
always the question, how much of all of this was written after
the time it had already become largely moot? Right, that's also the
question we asked before, right? How much of this was actually practiced
or was it theoretical?
So but I mean,
even in the time of the
rabbis, Rabbi Eliezer and, I mean if they did חולין בטהרה, hullin
betaharah, they might have had תרומה, terumah, that's true. The גמרא Gemara
discussed that before. They could have תרומה terumah even after the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash is destroyed. All right, let's go on. אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, ובשל נחושת, uveshel nechoshet, we make it out of brass.
I'm not sure why, does it not rust? What's the benefit of
brass? It more visible? I'm not sure. Okay, Charlie, just does brass
rust?
Not not in the way.
No, no, not brass, it's copper, right? נחושת Nechoshes copper. Copper definitely
rusts.
נחושת Nechoshes
is copper, right?
Yeah. What's brass? Is there a word for brass? Or ברזל? Barzel?
No, ברזל Barzel is iron. Okay, I don't know.
Anyway. What's what's copper? Brass is copper and iron? Copper and steel?
Oh wait, no, steel is something else. I don't know. Moving on.
כדתניא. Kidetanya. Like we learned by רבי יהודה אומר, רואין אותו כגבולין
של איזוב, Rebbe Yehudah Omer Ro'in Oso Kegivolin Shel Ezov, כאילו הן
של נחושת. Ke'ilu Hen Shel Nechoshes. Remember we actually discussed this a
few days
ago
that that you need a minimum amount of water from
the פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah
that it be a legitimate a valid sprinkling, enough that could get
on the tips of the of the hyssop and be sprinkled. That's
the minimum שיעור Shiur requirement. So so this ברייתא Braisa teaches us
in the name of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah that that, you know,
the tips of the of the hyssop will absorb, so maybe that's
a lot of water? He says no, it's as if you imagine
the hyssop was made out of copper. It was not absorbent. And
how much water would it require to go on the top and
to be sprinkled if you're dealing with a non-absorbent material? So he
uses copper as the example of non-absorbent.
Brass is copper and zinc.
Copper and zinc, got it. Okay, רבי יהודה אומר Rebbe Yehudah Omer,
רואין אותו כגבולין
של איזוב, Ro'in Oso Kegivolin Shel Ezov, you look at the sort
of the the whatever they're called, the ears of the hyssop, כאילו
הן של נחושת, Ke'ilu Hen Shel Nechoshes, they're like they're of copper.
So therefore you see it's not absorbent. אמר רב פפא שמע מינה,
Amar Rav Pappa Shema Mina, now that we see all these concerns
that it'll cause that tight-fitting and their response is that it'll cause
him to be more sexually excited and lead to more carry, we
hear from this, מכנסיים אסורים, Michnasayim Asurim, you're not allowed to have
underwear, because it causes and we're back, see we didn't get out
of that discussion. It leads to more זרע לבטלה. Zera Levatala. והכתיב,
Vehakesiv, doesn't the verse say, ועשה להם מכנסי בד, Ve'aseh Lahem Michnesei
Vad, that the כהנים Kohanim wore underwear of linen, לכסות בשר ערווה,
Lechasos Besar Ervah, to cover up their nakedness? ההוא כדתניא, Hahu Kidetanya,
that's like we learned in a ברייתא, Braisa, מכנסי כהנים למה הם
דומים, Michnesei Kohanim Lemah Hem Domim, what are they like, the underwear
of the כהנים? Kohanim? כמין פמלניא של פרשים, Kemin Pamalnya Shel Parashim,
like a type of a skirt of those that ride on horses,
of the what do they call them, charioteers. מלמעלה עד מתנים מלמטה
עד
ירכים, Milmalah Ad Masnayim Milmatah Ad Yerechayim, to the above it goes
as high as the as the loins, the thighs, and below up
to the calves. Okay, so basically they're like huge boxer shorts. Okay,
so fine, or jams, or bloomers. Okay, so right, bloomers he said?
Okay, fine. So that is not going to be tight around the
genital area that will lead to sexual excitement. ויש להם שנצים, Veyeish
Lahem Shnatzim, they have like like what do you call them, straps,
or you know, like I mean I'm imagining it's like what do
they, you know, like they're elastic strings, drawstrings, thank you. ואין להם
בית הנקב ולא בית הערווה, Veein Lahem Beis Hanekev Velo Beis Haervah,
they do not have a hole opposite to urinate or to defecate
from, right? Like some boxer shorts have at least for urinating they
have like a hole in the front, so you'd have to pull
them down if you needed to go to the bathroom. Okay, I
guess all of that is to make it very non-form-fitting and very
much not so of course the question is how do we do
it nowadays? I don't know. Maybe we assume that the way the
underwear is made- it's actually interesting whether anybody is מקפיד Makpid on
this. Is underwear made nowadays in a way where say it's not
as much of an issue? I don't know.
What's the- oh, there we have it.
Oh, now we have, right, undershirt with a הכשר Hechsher from the
בד"ץ, Badatz, right? Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so just to finish
this discussion up, רוכבי גמלים, Rochvei Gemalim, top of י"ד ע"א, Yud
Daled Amud Aleph, אסורים לאכול
בתרומה.
Asurim
Le'echol Beterumah. If you ride on camels, you can't eat תרומה. Terumah.
Why? Because you're always rubbing against it and it's leading to a
concern of קרי. Keri. Why more than horses? So presumably as we'll
see in a minute that people would ride on camels more bareback
than on horses and therefore there would be more rubbing, against also
skin against skin or like obviously with some type of a cloth
between it, but nevertheless, and therefore it was a greater concern. תניא
נמי הכי, Tanya Nami Hachi, we taught similarly, רוכבי גמלים כולם רשעים,
Rochvei Gemalim Kulam Reshaim, those who ride on camels they're all wicked,
because they're all concerned about קרי. Keri. And it goes back to
the גמרא Gemara yesterday about, you know, you're called a רשע Rasha
if you have זרע לבטלה. Zera Levatala. הספנים, Hasapanim, those that go
on the ships, כולם צדיקים, Kulam Tzadikim, they're all righteous. Why is
that?
Because they make so many vows, you know, when they're at sea.
Oh, so that's right, that's right. So you'd say, I mean you
could say they're going on ships and you're away from society and
men are away from their wives, so it's, you know, more concerns
about their sexual thoughts and so on, you know, there's the whole
all of the stories about sailors and whatever. But the גמרא Gemara
assumes like we know exactly, because they're always in סכנה, Sakanah, so
they're always calling out to God. So it's the יונה Yonah story.
Right, exactly, like the יונה Yonah story.
חמורין, Chamorin, when it comes to donkey riders, drivers, or riders, מהם
רשעים ומהם צדיקים, Mehem Reshaim Umehem Tzadikim, you know, they're like everybody,
some are רשעים, Reshaim, some צדיקים. Tzadikim. We can't exactly
categorize. איכא דאמרי, Ika Deamri, some say it actually depends on the
circumstances, הא דמחף והא דלא מחף, Ha Demachaf Veha Dela Machaf, it
depends if they wear saddles or not. If you wear saddles on
your donkey then you're a צדיק, Tzadik, if you don't you're a
רשע Rasha because it leads to זרע לבטלה, Zera Levatala, it leads
to seminal. Some say הא דמטרתין הא דלא מטרתין *ha demitartin ha
delo
mitartin*. That depends whether you ride מטרתין *mitartin* is the Aramaic word
for a balanced seat, so basically it means if you ride split-legged
or what's called sidesaddle.
Straddle. Okay, straddle. If you straddle it, you ride, you know, then
it's again the problem about the rubbing and so on. If you
ride sidesaddle, then it is not that problem.
Sidesaddle's dangerous. So this is another of these.
Well, for donkeys I guess it depends if you're going on a
high incline. Donkeys walk pretty slow, don't they? But they would use
donkeys because they could be good at like at going at good
angles, right? They're very sure-footed.
Mules are even better.
Better, right. All right. So the Gemara says רבי Rabbi יהושע בן
לוי לייט אמן דגני אפרקיד *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi layit aman degani
aparkid*. So he would curse, remember we had the curse before about
the hand, which we finally decided was a curse. So he cursed
people that would sleep on their, now אפרקיד *aparkid*, what does it
mean? It's generally assumed it means on their back.
Wait, what does דגני *degani* mean?
Sleep. Sleep. On their, yes, on their back. It could mean on
their front, but either way it's a concern again about a man
getting an erection through sleeping.
So Rashi's concerned that if a man sleeps on his back the
erection is visible, so it's, you know, it's shameful.
Wait, are they supposed to cover?
No, they don't say that. Or, but some say that it's also
the way, yeah, if the body, so if it's on the front
you'd be concerned about the genitals rubbing against the bed, but there
was also a concern somehow that if it's the back somehow the
back of the spine, the lower spine rubs against the bed and
that somehow was a concern that could lead to an erection. One
way or the other there was a concern that it would lead
to an erection or the erection would be visible.
Could it be the material of the sheets?
That's what Michael said. Right, that's what Michael said. Yeah, it could
be. I mean Rashi and Tosafot don't say that but it's a
reasonable explanation. Okay, so now the Gemara goes on.
Oh, Rashi also mentions, I'm sorry, that if a person is sleeping
on his back his hand have greater access to his genital area
in his sleep so not necessarily intentionally, but again that rubbing would
cause that unintentional, in his sleep, would cause an erection. איני *eini*,
is that really true? ואמר רב יוסף אפרקיד לא יקרא קריאת שמע
Shema, *veamar Rav Yosef aparkid lo yikra keri'at shema*, that if somebody
is lying on his back he should not say שמע Shema? *shema*.
קריאת שמע Shema הוא דלא יקרא *keri'at shema hu delo yikra*, to
say שמע Shema *shema* again makes it not respectful, not exactly clear
why, but המיגנא שפיר דמי *ha-migna shapir dami*, that's only a sleeping
problem? But sleeping is fine? But sleeping is fine. It's only a
שמע *shema* problem? Yeah, we do. I mean but we'll see in
a minute a qualification. Sleeping is okay? So the Gemara says like
this: לענין מיגנא *le-inyan migna*, when it comes to sleeping, כי מצלי
*ki matzli*, it's funny, מצלי *matzli* is also word for davening, but
here it means when you're leaning a little bit, שפיר דמי *shapir
dami*, it's okay. Meaning it's just if you're totally flat on your
back. A little bit of a tilt, a little on an angle
is okay. לענין קריאת שמע *le-inyan keri'at shema*, when it comes to
שמע *shema*, כי מצלי אסור *ki matzli assur*, even a little of
a tilt is not appropriate because that's not considered respectful. Unless you're
totally sort of like lying on your side, that's different. But if
you're fundamentally on your back, look, if somebody is in a hospital
and sick and whatever, obviously these things are different. Also now you
can nowadays you can make the beds so you're sitting half sitting
up. Anyway, והא רבי Rabbi יוחנן מצלי וקרי קריאת שמע *veha Rabbi
Yochanan matzli vekari keri'at shema*, what, what do you mean? Rabbi Yochanan
would incline a little bit and say שמע *shema*. So the Gemara
says שאני רבי Rabbi יוחנן דבעל בשר הוה *shani Rabbi Yochanan debaal
basar hava*. Rabbi Yochanan was very heavy. It's so funny, somehow whenever
I imagine the Tannaim and Amoraim, I always imagine them as like
pretty fit, you
know, but actually, it's interesting because you know Yaakov Elman, you know,
obviously who deals also, although Rabbi Yochanan was in Eretz Yisrael, but
this is the Bavli's view of Rabbi Yochanan. But anyway, Rabbi Yochanan
was supposed to be very handsome also, wasn't he? I'm not sure
if that's how handsome he is or am I confusing him. Resh
Lakish. Resh Lakish. No, anyway, they said Rabbi Yochanan
was very,
yeah anyway, but the, you know, but in person, you know, in
Bavel, you know, in the idea of the sage, you know, also
you actually see this in the Far Eastern like a Buddha, right?
Right, like the big, heavy people. So anyway, so again, the Gemara
says that Rabbi Yochanan was very heavy, so therefore it would have
been maybe too difficult to sit up or to totally turn on
his side, so they were more lenient. So you see it's not
an absolute.
Do you remember the story, I forgot which Masechet it was, that
the two of them when they stand belly-to-belly could drive a chariot.
Oh right, right, right. That's right. Yep. Okay. So now the Gemara
continues.
Guy lying on the street saying שמע *shema* because they wanted to
do it first thing.
You did it like בשכבך *beshokhbekha*, by בשכבך *beshokhbekha* does that mean
lying on the back? בשכבך *beshokhbekha* could mean lying on the side.
Remember in the Gemara, right, the way you would eat in Roman
times would be reclining. So that's more reclining than it means straight
lying on one's back. Okay. Back to שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*
of these days you said that.
Yeah, at least unless there's extenuating circumstances.
משנה Mishna *Mishna*. I'm most concerned about the underwear.
Yeah,
say שמע *shema* but
not on your,
yeah, not
flat on your back.
All right, ויתר *veiter*, דרך derech, בנות ישראל *derech benot yisrael*. Now
we have yet to get out of the checking before sex and
you know, it's, I would say that although the Gemara said before.
Before and after, if you're paying attention, the משניות Mishnayos are a
little bit unclear. Because the משנה Mishna before said, said that they
check כשהן הולכות לשמש את המטה keshehen holchos lishtamesh b’mita when they’re
going to have sex. Okay, that was an earlier, the earlier משנה
Mishna said. This one is going to talk about after sex. Okay,
and the simple reading of the משנה Mishna. I would say is,
is that before sex it's strictly required, again this is in the
context of עסוקה בטהרות, asuka b’tahros, after sex is a nice, is
a commendable practice. But the גמרא Gemara reads that both before and
after, at least for the time of עסוקה בטהרות asuka b’tahros is
strictly required. Before because, you know, and again there could be different
reasons. After could be you consider that sex brings on bleeding, and
before because of a concern that you shouldn’t be having sex when
you’re a נדה. nida. But again all of this is in the
context of עסוקה בטהרות. asuka b’tahros.
Do you say that he pulls it out right away it doesn’t
do a good בדיקה? bedika?
Does do a... yes, but you do as good... at least it's
something. It doesn’t do a full job. Okay.
Women saying שמע, they don’t get into that women saying שמע?
In ברכות, Brachos, well, in ברכות Brachos actually there is some but
even in ברכות Brachos the discussion is primarily about men. There’s questions
about men saying שמע with women in the bed or whatever, I’d
have to remember. But you’re right.
They said שמוץ... Shmutz...
and and but you’re right the discussion is basically about men.
Now generally the discussion in the גמרא Gemara except in מסכת נדה
Maseches Nida is about men. Although by שמע at least it's a
מצוה mitzvah on men and not the women, but you know, but
anyway but you’re right. ברכות Brachos is coming up! Normally I'd say
we'll get to it in three years, we'll get to that in
two months. Okay let’s take a look. Next משנה. Mishna דרך בנות
ישראל משמשות בשני עדים. derech benos Yisrael mishamshos b’shnei edim. So before
it said women do check before sex, this says דרך, the way
is. Okay and again I think the simple sense of the משנה
Mishna means that it was commendable to do it after, it was
required before. Again, when עסוקה בטהרות. asuka b’tahros. Okay but the גמרא
Gemara says you have to do it before and after. So the
way of Jewish women is to is to have sex with two
witnesses, not literally, obviously, with two cloths, אחד לו ואחד לה, echad
lo v’echad lah, one for him, one for her. So they would
wipe themselves after sex and see if they were bleeding they would
check afterwards. Okay it's a little late then, but again the concern
may be that they became that it brought about bleeding. והצנועות מתקנות
שלישי לתקן את הבית. v’hazniyos matkinos shlishi l’saken es habayis. And the
and the particularly
literally modest ones but scrupulous ones would have a third cloth for
to check beforehand. לתקן l’saken to prepare the house. Okay again the
whole metaphor of the house. Now of course what do you mean?
Before you said they have to, now you’re saying צנועות. tzniyos. So
even in the משנה Mishnah there’s a contradiction about required versus commendable
and this really makes it just like oh the really פרום frum
ones. So again the גמרא Gemara before said that meant they wouldn’t
use the same cloth twice. But again there is a con there
is a problem in the משניות you know what would be demanded
and what would be commendable. Okay so but anyway you have it
before and after. Now regarding the after, נמצא על שלו, nimtza al
shelo, if his cloth that he wiped himself afterwards has blood on
it, טמאים וחייבין בקרבן. t’meiyim v’chayavin b’korban. Then they’re definitely both טמאים
t’meiyim because it was he was bleeding when they were having sex,
how else did it get on him? This obviously is his genital
area and they have to bring a קרבן korban because now they
both did an איסור כרת. issur kareis. They had sex when, notice
the plural, they both have to, because they did an איסור כרת
issur kareis when she was a נדה. nida. Now why is it
not considered an אונס oness is a good question. If he has
a וסת קבוע veset kavua and it's not the time of the
וסת, veset, then why is that a שוגג? shogeg? Okay this raises
larger questions about do is being thoughtless enough to get you out
of being a קרבן korban bringing a קרבן? korban?
And I will just give you one extreme example the answer is
no, where the גמרא Gemara speaks in שבת Shabbos about a תינוק
שנשבה בין הגוים, tinok shenishba bein hagoyim, somebody who grew up and
never I’ve mentioned it before we had it also in פסחים, Pesachim,
never knew he was Jewish, had no idea, never knew had no
reason to think and this person obviously doesn't keep שבת Shabbos and
then finds out twenty years later that he’s Jewish. And it says
he has to bring a קרבן. korban. He doesn't have to bring
a קרבן korban for every שבת Shabbos or for every מלאכה melacha
but he has to bring a קרבן. korban. Why does he have
to bring a קרבן? korban? He was complete אונס. oness. So you
see that if you perpetrated a sin we discussed this when we
did כריתות, Krisos, the fact that there is a sin in the
world this metaphysical reality of being violation it needs to be fixed
and you’re the one who has to fix by a קרבן korban
even if you’re faultless, which is quite fascinating but I mention it
here because it seems that you know why are they to blame?
But it doesn't matter they did the sin it means a קרבן.
korban. But that is a larger question about אונס oness by קרבנות.
korbanos. Now נמצא על שלה, nimtza al shela, if it's on her
cloth, אותם, osam, if she checks immediately, that’s a word to mean
like instantaneously and we discussed that before, טמאים וחייבין בקרבן. t’meiyim v’chayavin
b’korban. They’re טמאים t’meiyim and they have to bring a קרבן korban
because if it was immediate you assume you have to assume it
was there when they were having sex. נמצא על שלה לאחר זמן,
nimtza al shela l’achar zman, if it was after a few minutes
or not even more than instantaneously, טמאים מספק, t’meiyim misafeik, they were
doubtful טמאים. t’meiyim. Again twenty-four hours is rabbinic but going back a
few minutes that's a real doubt so they’re doubtfully טמאים t’meiyim ופטורין
מן הקרבן, u’pturin min hakorban, and they’re exempt from the קרבן korban
because you don’t know that you sinned but they both are טמאים
t’meiyim because there’s a good chance that she was a נדה nida
when they were having sex.
You want to know אשם תלוי? asham talui?
Well the גמרא Gemara will discuss that. איזו אחר זמן, eizu achar
zman, what does it mean after a while? כדי שתירד מן המיטה
ותדיח פניה *Kedei shetared min hamita veta'adiach paneha*, the time it takes
to get off the bed and to wipe herself. Once it's past
that time, then it's only a ספק safek *safek*, it's not immediate.
No,
פניה *paneha* presumably פניה של מטה *paneha shel mata*, it's a euphemism.
Wash the pubic area. ואחר כך מטמא מעת לעת *Ve'achar kach metamei
me'et le'et*. Afterwards, after that immediate time, then, so there's immediate, there's
after immediate, then there's after the after. So after the after, it's
not within a minute or two, but it's more than that, then
it's all rabbinic. Then it's 24, it goes back 24 hours to
the last time she checked, but it's all rabbinic. ואינו מטמא את
בועלה *Ve'eino metamei et bo'ala*. He's טמא tamei *tamei*, but the husband
is not for this rabbinic טומאה tumah *tumah* of 24 hours as
opposed to when it's a real definite or a real possibility, then
we had this leniency at least vis-a-vis her husband, literally the one
who had sex with her, that he is not טמא tamei? *tamei*
but she is.
Or until the last בדיקה bedika *bedikah* if
she did it in short time. רבי Rabbi, עקיבא אומר אף מטמא
את בועלה *Rabbi Akiva omer af metamei et bo'ala*. Rabbi Akiva says
no, it's across the board. She's טמאה temeiah. *tmeiah* and the husband
is if they had sex. מודין חכמים לרבי עקיבא ברואה כתם kesem,
*Modin chachamim leRabbi Akiva bero'ah ketem*. Now they agree, and this is
a little ironic, that if it was a כתם kesem. *ketem* and
not an actual through a check, then שמתמא את בועלה *shemetamei et
bo'ala*, the husband is. Now why? כתמים *ketamim* on the one hand
are more rabbinic. They might be more lenient, but on the other
hand, there's a greater question about when did you actually have, when
did that actually the stain come about? If she checks, does an
internal check 10 minutes later, then most likely she wasn't bleeding 10
minutes ago, because then she would have felt it or she would
have seen it, if she's actually finding it in her body 10
minutes later. But if she finds it on the cloth 10 minutes
later, on the bedspread 10 minutes later, it could have easily been
there 10 minutes ago. So although כתמים *ketamim* on the one hand
are more rabbinic because they could have come from elsewhere, they didn't
necessarily come from the woman, the way we treat the past, it
can be more strict by כתמים *ketamim* because there's a greater likelihood
they really did come from the past. And you will also remember
that by כתמים *ketamim* we don't go back 24 hours, we go
back to the last time the things were laundered. So it could
be much longer that we go back for the same reason.
We never assume it's from him unless from a בדיקה bedika *bedikah*.
We will assume it's from him if he's got a cut or
other reasons that he might be bleeding. But without that, we will
not assume it's from him, that's for sure. Okay, but if it's
a כתם kesem *ketem*, כתם kesem, *ketem* is more possible it came
from random sources, bedbugs or who knows what. Okay, let's look at
the גמרא Gemara *gemara*. וניחוש דילמא דם dam, מאכולת הוא *Venichush dilma
dam ma'acholet hu*, which is exactly what the גמרא Gemara *gemara* asks.
Why even when you do an internal check, she's definitely טמאה temeiah,
*tmeiah* and brings a קרבן *korban*, all these things, maybe there was
a louse right there in the pubic area? They were not such
a hygienic society. So maybe that it's blood of a louse even
from an internal check. The cloth touches the area, the body in
that area. אמר רב זירא אותו מקום בדוק הוא אצל מאכולת *Amar
Rav Zeira oto makom baduk hu etzel ma'acholet*. No, that place, the
pubic space, and again we're not just talking internally but presumably the
pubic hair as well, which is maybe where more where lice could
be, we know no lice are there, we're not concerned about that.
Little bit's checked, but doesn't because she checked it, we'll see in
the גמרא *gemara* in a minute that literally means like there's no
concern that there are lice there. ואיכא דאמרי סחיף דחיקא ליה למאכולת
*Ve'ika de'amrei sachif dechika lei lema'acholet*. No, it's too tight for lice
to be there, which then presumably maybe is talking about internally, I
don't know. So the גמרא *gemara* says מאי בינייהו *mai beineihu*? What's
the difference? Rav Moshe has a whole תשובה *tshuvah* where he discusses
some aspects. Anyway, איכא בינייהו דאשתכח מאכולת רצופה *Ika beineihu de'ishtakach ma'acholet
retzufa*. That the louse is actually, you found a louse on the
בדיקה bedika *bedikah* cloth and it's basically smooshed, smooshed on the בדיקה
bedika *bedikah* cloth. Okay, so that's pretty good evidence that the stain
is from the louse. So let's understand why we're assuming we normally
aren't concerned about it. ללישנא דאמר בדוקו *Lelishna de'amar baduku*, according to
the approach that lice are never there, היכי אמטאי *heichi amtai*? So
then never there, never there, how did you get a smooshed louse?
After the cloth was removed, somehow the louse came on the cloth,
but we would assume it never happened, so that louse must have
been from elsewhere.
ללישנא דאמר דחיקו *Lelishna de'amar dechiku*, but if it's just that it's
normally too difficult for lice to get there, but not impossible, אימא
שמש רצפה *eima shamash ritzpa*. So then I could say that the
louse was actually there and yes it was tight, but the שמש
*shamash*, the male genitals or the penis in the act of sex
caused it to get somehow smooshed. Okay, it didn't have a lot
of space, but it was there and it got smooshed. So anyway,
the גמרא *gemara* is assuming that somehow it's according to one version
it's possible a louse would be there but unlikely, but if there's
actually evidence that it was there because it's on the cloth and
it's smooshed, we'll assume it was there and the blood was from
the louse. But if however, but if however, we say it's never
there, then even if Even if there's a smushed louse, we'll assume
it wasn't there. Of course, I don't get it. Even if it
wasn't there, maybe the blood came from the louse afterwards? Yes, I
don't know. Somehow we're assuming that we know the blood was at
the time of the checking and the question is when did the
louse come? Okay, so the גמרא goes on, איתמר, itmar, we taught,
we talked, בדקה בעד הבדוק לה, badka b'eid habaduk lah, she checked
with a checked cloth, right, a cloth that had been checked and
was known to have been, I'm sorry, did I skip a line?
Listen, yeah, no, okay. She checked with a cloth that was known
to have been clean and had been checked, so there was no
louse on the cloth from beforehand,
okay? ותחבו בירכה, v'tchavo beyarecha, after she did her internal check, check,
accidentally touched it against her thigh. ולמחר מצאה עליו דם, ul'machar matzah
alav dam, and then the next day she found on it, what's
it? So עד eid is masculine,
ירך yerech is feminine, it's on her... wait, did I say that
right? I said the opposite. There's actually מחלוקת machlokes רש"י, Rashi, תוספות.
Tosafos. One minute, no, yeah, I'm right, so she found on the
thigh, there was blood on her thigh. She didn't find blood on
the cloth, she found blood on the thigh, okay, what are we
going to say? So אמר רב טמאה נדה, amar Rav temeiah niddah,
she's a נדה, niddah, we have to assume that what happened, the
blood came from the cloth to the thigh because it was where
she touched her thigh and therefore it was from a check and
therefore she's טמאה. temeiah. אמר ליה, amar lei, wait, wait,
but this cloth then, we should... the next day it didn't have
any blood on it?
It just... maybe they threw it out or it didn't have cloth...
let me take a look at what רש"י Rashi says.
Yeah, it doesn't discuss what... you know, what's the story with the
cloth. But you would think that you would... the cloth, right. So
presumably the cloth is not around to be checked.
אמר ליה רב שימי בר חייא מה חוששת אמרת לן? amar lei
Rav Shimi bar Chiyya mah chosheshes amart lan? One minute, last time
you told us that הלכה, halacha, you told us in that case
she's חוששת, chosheshes, it's a ספק that she's טמאה, temeiah. not a
definite טמאה. temeiah איתמר נמי, itmar nami, so no answer to that.
איתמר נמי, itmar nami, we talked similarly, אמר שמואל טמאה נדה, amar
Shmuel temeiah niddah, in that case she's טמאה נדה. temeiah niddah. וכן
מורים בבי מדרשא, v'chein morin b'bei midrasha, and that's what they teach
in the בית מדרש, beis medrash, טמאה נדה. temeiah niddah. So there,
sounds like
it was a relatively common case if they were having all these
discussions. איתמר, itmar, was taught, בדקה בעד שאינו בדוק לה, badka b'eid
she'eino baduk lah, let's say the cloth had not been checked beforehand.
So who knows, maybe there was a louse's blood on it from
beforehand? והניחתו בקופסא, v'hinnichto b'kufsa, and it was left in a box
after checking, ולמחר, ul'machar, meaning, so obviously nothing else came on... came
from it after checking because it was in a protected box. ולמחר
מצאה עליו דם, ul'machar matzah alav dam, and then you checked it
and there was blood. So what's the הלכה? halacha? Do we say
that it had to come from the woman or do we say
that since it wasn't checked from beforehand that maybe there was a
blood stain on it from a louse from beforehand? Or maybe because
it was in the box, although it was in a box something
happened, so what do you say about that? אמר רב יוסף כל
ימיו של רבי חייא טימא, amar Rav Yosef kol yamav shel Rabbi
Chiyya timma, of the whole life of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya he
was saying such a case the woman is טמאה. temeiah ולעת זקנותו
טיהר, ul'eis ziknuso tihar, but when he got older he softened a
little on this הלכה halacha and he said she was טהורה, tehorah,
we assume that it was from beforehand. איבעיא להו היכי קאמר, ibaia
lehu heichi ka'amar, he asked, what did he... what do you mean?
כל ימיו טימא משום נדה, kol yamav timma mishum niddah, his whole
life he said she was a definite נדה niddah in that case.
ולעת זקנותו טיהר, ul'eis ziknuso tihar, and when he got older he
said she was טהור tahor meaning not definite נדה, niddah, משום נדה
וטימא משום כתם, mishum niddah v'timma mishum kesem, at least it's a
rabbinic טומאה of a stain, at least it's a possibility it came
from her, so it's rabbinic, it's not biblical.
או דלמא כל ימיו טימא משום כתם, o dilma kol yamav timma
mishum kesem, no, from the very outset because the... the cloth wasn't
checked, from the very outset he said it was rabbinic, it was
a כתם, kesem it was a stain that we assume was from
her but we don't know for sure, so it was rabbinic.
ולעת זקנותו טיהר מכל וכל, ul'eis ziknuso tihar mikol v'chol, he said
she's completely טהור. tahor. So which stage did he start with and
where did he end up? תא שמע, ta shema, come hear, דתניא,
detanya, it was taught in a ברייתא, braisa, בדקה בעד שאינו בדוק
לה, badka b'eid she'eino baduk lah,
if she checked again exactly with this, with a cloth unchecked, by
the way תוספות Tosafos says it doesn't mean completely unchecked because, you
know, like something that looked like that high likelihood that there were
stains on it, because then nobody would say she's טמאה נדה. temeiah
niddah. It means that you hadn't done a good checking of it,
but it was assumed to be pretty good, okay? והניחתו בקופסא, v'hinnichto
b'kufsa, put it in a box.
ולמחר מצאה עליו דם, ul'machar matzah alav dam, exactly our case. רבי
אומר טמאה משום נדה ורבי חייא אומר טמאה משום כתם. Rabbi omer
temeiah mishum niddah v'Rabbi Chiyya omer temeiah mishum kesem. רבי Rabbi says
she's definitely טמאה temeiah. as a נדה niddah biblically and רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiyya says no, rabbinic as a כתם. kesem Now we have
to figure out was this in his old age or his young
age so we'll know which... whether he started or ended with this.
So אמרו לו לרבי חייא, amru lo l'Rabbi Chiyya, so... so רבי
Rebbi said to רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya,
I'm sorry, אמר לו רבי חייא, amar lo Rabbi Chiyya, רבי Rebbi,
said... רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya said to רבי, Rebbi אי אתה מודה
שצריכה כגריס ועוד? i ata modeh shetzricha kegris v'od? But don't you
admit in this case that she's not טמאה temeiah, until it's the
size of a lentil bean? Meaning you admit that in this case
there's a concern it came from a louse, and when you're concerned
it came from a louse it has to be bigger than the
size of a lentil bean or you assume it's louse blood, but
if it's a louse... because louse blood would not be that big.
So he said to רבי Rebbi look, you've got to admit to
me she's not definitely טמאה. temei'ah We treat it like a stain.
One of the laws of stains is that we say if a
stain is bigger than the size of a lentil bean, basically it's
about the size of, there's debate, penny, a nickel, let's say a
nickel, if it's smaller than that size then she's not טמאה, temei'ah
that's one of the laws of a stain as opposed to something
that's on... on a בדיקה cloth on an internal check. So we
said look, you admit it has the laws of stains, less than
the size of a lentil bean it's not a problem, so you're
showing that you're treating it as a כתם ketem, not as a
נדה niddah so why do you say נדה? niddah? So אמר ליה
amar lei אבל, abal, yes, you're right, actually אבל abal in old
משנה Hebrew meant yes. אמר ליה amar lei so רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiyya said back, ואם תאמר, ve'im tomar, אף אתה עושה אותו ככתם,
af ata oseh oto kekesem, so you're treating it like a כתם,
ketem not like a נדה. niddah. ורבי סבר, verebbi savar, רבי Rebbi
would say, בעינן כגריס ועוד ba'inan kegris ve'od לאפוקי מדמי מאכולת, le'afokei
midmei macholes, I admit you need it to be that size of
a lentil bean so it's not considered to be louse blood. ובדיקא
דנפיק מדמי מאכולת, uvdika denafik midmei macholes, once I can discount the
possibility of louse blood, ודאי מגופא אתי, vadai migufa asei, it definitely
came from her and it's נדה niddah because in the end it
wasn't on her sheets, it was on a בדיקה cloth. So you
can have a middle category. Normally a בדיקה cloth, the הלכה halacha
is if it's a problem, it's biblical and even the tiniest drop
of blood, and if it's a stain on the cloth, it's rabbinic
and it needs to be a certain size, but this is a
middle category. It was through an internal check, so Rebbi says, I
have to, because it was checked, the cloth, I have to discount
a louse, but once I can discount a louse, I can put
it into the בדיקה category and not the כתם category and say
she's a definite נדה. niddah. So it's an interesting middle category. Now
we have to ask our question whether this was רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiyya when he was old or young. So מאי לאו בזקנותו קאי,
mai lav bizknuso kai, so you see that he was in an
old age, הא בילדותו טימיה משום נדה, ha beyalduso timyei mishum niddah,
so must mean that when he was young, he said like Rebbi,
she was a נדה niddah definite biblical, and now he's older he's
saying only a כתם and he's moving away from that. שמע מינה,
shma mina, that's a good proof. Now how do we know he
said this when he was old, maybe he said it when he
was young? So רש״י Rashi says
because he argued with him. So he was Rebbi's teacher, he wouldn't
have argued with him unless he was already older. תוספות Tosafot says,
what do you mean, students argue with the רבם rabam all the
time.
So תוספות Tosafot says it's because he did not introduce his question
with an honorific. He didn't say רבי, Rebbi you know, היך קסברת,
eich kasavarta, he just said what he said, his challenge. So that
shows that he was already at the stage of being a colleague
and it was not a what do you call it, and it
was not a, what do you call it, and he was older.
Okay, so now the גמרא says like this.
משתבח ליה רבי לרבי ישמעאל ברבי
יוסי לרבי חמא בר ביסא. mishtabach lei Rebbi le'Rebbi Yishmael beRebbi Yosi
le'Rebbi Chama bar Bisa. Rebbi used to be praising Rabbi Ishmael b'Rabbi
Yosi to Rabbi Chama bar Bisa. Oh what a great guy is
Rabbi Ishmael b'Rabbi Yosi. אדם גדול, adam gadol, he's a great guy.
אמר ליה, amar lei, no, so he said to him, Rabbi Chama
bar Bisa, לכשיבא לידך הביאהו לידי. lichsheyavo leyadecha havi'eihu leyadai. Next time
he visits, bring him to me. I want to see this great
guy. כי אתא אמר ליה. ki ata amar lei. So when he
came he said to him. So now Rabbi Ishmael b'Rabbi Yosi is
being brought to Rabbi Chama bar Bisa. Rabbi Chama bar Bisa said
to him, בעי מיני מילתא. ba'ei minei milta. Ask me a question.
So maybe based on your question I'll see how smart you are.
בעי מיניה, ba'ei minei, so he asked him, בדקה בעד שאינו בדוק
לה והניחה בקופסא ולמחר מצאה עליה דם
מהו. badka be'ed she'eino baduk lah vehinnichah bekupsa ulemachar matzah aleha dam
mahu. So of all the questions, a woman checks with this unchecked
cloth, finds it the next day, checks the box, finds דם, what's
the הלכה? halacha? אמר ליה, amar lei, כדברי אבא אימא לך או
כדברי רבי אימא לך. kedivrei abba eimar lach o kedivrei Rebbi eimar
lach. Should I tell you like my father said, Rabbi Yosi, or
should I tell you what Rebbi said? אמר ליה, amar lei, כדברי
רבי, kedivrei Rebbi, tell me what Rebbi says, אימא לי. eima li.
אמר רבי ישמעאל, amar Rabbi Yishmael, so Rabbi Yishmael said, זהו שאומרים
עליו אדם גדול הוא? zehu she'omrim alav adam gadol hu? This is
the person you were praising, what a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
he is? היך מניחין דברי הרב ושומעין דברי התלמיד? eich manichin divrei
harav veshomin divrei hatalmid? How do they ask to abandon the Rebbi,
because Rabbi Yosi was a teacher of Rebbi, and ask to hear
what the student thought, what Rebbi said? Now by the way it
was also a slight to Rebbi, it's like Rebbi was praising this
guy, so how big of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham he is,
he wants to see what you said rather than what my father
said. Like an interesting dynamic going on here. רבי חמא בר ביסא
סבר, Rabbi Chama bar Bisa savar,
so why did Rabbi Chama bar Bisa ask to hear
about what Rebbi said? Oh I think I got the,
oh I'm sorry, I apologize, no. Was that right?
Yeah, no, Rabbi Chama bar Bisa, right. No, no, I'm sorry. I'm
sorry. I got the who was being praised and who was being
brought before, I got the order wrong. I forget which I said
it but Rebbi was praising Rabbi Chama bar Bisa, I'm sorry I
think I said it wrong. Rebbi was praising Rabbi Chama bar Bisa
to Rabbi Ishmael b'Rabbi Yosi. So Rabbi Ishmael b'Rabbi Yosi was the
one who was being brought in front of. So Rabbi Ishmael b'Rabbi
Yosi said you should have asked what my father Rabbi Yosi says,
why did you ask what Rebbi said? So what did Rabbi Chama
bar Bisa think? סבר רבי ריש מתיבתא הוה. savar Rebbi reish mesivta
hava. Look, Rebbi is the ראש ישיבה. rosh yeshiva. ושכיחי רבנן קמיה
veshchichi rabanan kamei and the rabbis are very often, like there's a
lot of learning around Rebbi, ומחדדין שמעתתיה umachdedin shmaysesei and therefore his,
you know, things get clarified better. So Rebbi although he's a תלמיד
talmid of Rabbi Yosi, things get more clarified around, you know, Rebbi
has a sharper understanding of things because he's the head of a
ישיבה yeshiva where a lot of תורה Torah learning is always taking
place.
So, what? Rabbi Yosi, father, was a teacher of Rebbi but ultimately
not a ראש ישיבה. rosh yeshiva. Okay, so I think we are
going, do we have a second to do the next? I know
but I have to catch the bus. מאי רבי ומאי רבי יוסי
אמר רבה בר בר חנה תנא רבי mai Rebbi umai Rabbi Yosi
amar Rabbah bar bar Chana tanna Rebbi רבי מטמא רבי יוסי מטהר
Rebbi metamei Rebbi Yosi metaher and that's the two opinions that רבי
Rebbi said טמא tamei and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi said טהור. tahor.
ואמר רבי זירא כשטמא Ve-amar Rabbi Zeira keshe-timmei so therefore did you
want—so רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי Rabbi Ishmael bar Rebbi Yosi said
do you want my father says, which is טהור, tahor, do you
want what רבי Rebbi says, which is טמא? tamei So he asked
רבי and here the גמרא is now leaning towards טמא tamei, because
it says רבי knew it better. ואמר רבי זירא כשטמא רבי לרבי
מאיר כשטיהר רבי יוסי לעצמו טיהר. Ve-amar Rabbi Zeira keshe-timmei Rebbi le-Rebbi
Meir keshe-teher Rebbi Yosi le-atzmo teher.
When רבי said טמא tamei, it was like רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir,
and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi said טהור tahor he was following his
own opinion.
דתניא: De-tanya: האשה שהיתה עושה צרכיה וראתה דם, Ha-ishah she-hayetah osah tzarekheiha
ve-ra'atah dam, a woman who is urinating and saw blood, רבי מאיר
אומר עומדת טמאה יושבת טהורה. Rebbi Meir omer omedet temei'ah yoshevet tehorah.
If she stands she's טמאה because then it could it coming not
from the urine, not from the—whatever—the kidneys, but it's coming from the
uterus. That was his—way he read it. And if she's sitting she's
טהורה tehorah we can assume it's coming from the kidneys. רבי יוסי
אומר בין כך ובין כך טהורה. Rebbi Yosi omer bein kach u-vein
kach tehorah. Regardless she's טהורה. tehorah. So you see רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir is more inclined in this case to attribute it to uterine
blood and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi is more inclined to attribute it
to another source. So similarly by the unchecked cloth whether you think
it came from a louse or not, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would
be strict and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi would be lenient. אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרב אשי לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Acha berei
de-Rav Ashi le-Rav Ashi, והאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא כשטמא רבי מאיר
לא טימא אלא משום כתם? Ve-ha-amar Rabbi Yosi be-Rabbi Chanina keshe-timmei Rebbi
Meir lo timmei ella mishum ketem? But don't we say that when
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says in the case of the urine that
it was a problem, he only was saying it was a rabbinic,
it wasn't biblical? ואילו רבי משום נדה קאמר ליה. Ve-illu Rebbi mishum
niddah ka-amar lei. And רבי when he said that this case about
the unchecked cloth was טמא, treated it as a נדה niddah טמא,
that was his whole debate with רבי חייא. Rebbi Chiyya. אמר ליה
אנן הכי קאמרינן. Amar lei anan hachi ka-amrinan. Here's what I say.
No, when רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said the urine case he was
saying that it's not like a—it's not כתם, it's נדה, niddah, it's
biblical and therefore it's the same as—and therefore the positions line up.
That רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that when there's—that we're more inclined
even when there's another source like the possibility of the urine, he's
more inclined to say that it comes from—that she's טמאה and same
by the unchecked cloth and even טמאה נדה. temei'ah niddah. And the
other opinions are כתם or טהור לגמרי tahor legamrei in all these
cases about when there are various doubts about where the blood came
from. All right.